Guide to the Helen E. Hokinson Cartoons for The New Yorker
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Portfolio 4, Series IV
  - 7. "I wonder if wild rice would be a thrill for Colonel Parker?" (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 1/4 x 12 1/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. AA1598 written in blue crayon on verso, portion of first A and 8 cut away.
  - 8. "And now good bye, kiddies, till tomorrow. Remember your radio uncle is going to be very disappointed if you don't eat your vegetables." (Box 10, Folder 171)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 8 1/4 x 10 1/8". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. AA4066 on 6 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 9. Waiting for the girls to finish a clothes gabfest. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 1/4 x 9 1/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption of A Foursome. 3254 and highlites 8292/4-1-2/110 written in pencil on verso.
  - 10. "I can't decide whether to be Madame Yvonne or Mademoiselle Yvonne." (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 12 3/4 x 14 1/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption with different wording. AA7860 written in blue crayon on verso, portion of first A cut away.
  - 11. "Why, Mrs. Sedgwick, I had a feeling I'd meet someone in New York today!" (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 3/4 x 17 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption with different wording.
  - 12."I'm dying to ask him a few questions about Mabel Dodge Luhan!", 1938 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 16 3/4 x 14". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased captions with variant wording. AA7704 written in blue crayon on verso.
    Published in July 9, 1938, issue with the caption "Just a minute. I'm going to ask him a question or two about Mrs. Luhan!"
  - 13. [Road passing through French village under a house built over the road], circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Watercolor, 13 x 9 3/4"; drawn in France one summer in the late 1920s.
  - 14. [Road passing through hillside meadow, trees and mountain in background], circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Watercolor, 13 x 10"; drawn in France one summer in the late 1920s.
  - 15. [View from hillside of a village and its farm land beyond], circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Portfolio 5, Series V
  - 1. [Scene at the circus.], 1933 (Box 11, Folder 245)
    In each of three rings a pair gymnasts performs a balancing act—three do headstands on the end of long poles balanced on the shoulders of their partners while a large lady watches fearfully. Black ink and watercolor, 20 x 13". Date stamped Feb 15 1933 PM in lower right corner A6774 written in blue crayon on verso. Kraft paper cover sheet dated in pencil April 22 '33. Drawing for a cover published on issue of April 22, 1933.
  - 2. [Matron in fur coat on ladder in front of a bank of frozen food lockers handing a frozen turkey down to chauffeur.] (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Black ink and watercolor over pencil, 16 3/4 x 13 3/4"; unsigned. Rough sketch for cover.
  - 3. Paris Street. Try and cross one: the English Channel is nothing. (Box 11, Folder 246)
    A sequence of nine panel drawings. Black ink and gray wash over pencil, the drawings various sizes together on a sheet 20 x13 1/2". Title written in pencil at head of drawing no. 2 and cancelled.
  - 4. A taxi in Paris—and what happens after you get one. (Box 11, Folder 247)
    A sequence of ten panel drawings. Black ink and gray wash over pencil, the drawings, various sizes, together on a sheet 20 x 13 1/2". Title written in pencil above drawings 1 and 2, captions written in pencil at foot of each drawing. A2296 written in pencil on verso.
  - 5. [Scene at a country fair: matron with dog on leash and chauffeur viewing cakes and preserved fruits in jars at stand.] (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Pencil and watercolor, 17 3/8 x 14", unsigned. Rough sketch for cover.
  - 6. [Scene at outdoor church bazaar: matron and chauffeur arrives, each carrying a cake.] (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Pencil and watercolor, 15 x 16 1/2", unsigned. Notation—Mrs. Benedict—written in pencil at foot of drawing. Rough sketch for cover.
  - 7. "Oh Albert—I did something wrong on the Geo. Wash. Bridge.", 1938 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 17". Caption written in pencil at foot of Kraft paper cover, and date stamped in lower right corner APR 16 1938. AA7357 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 8. [Scene on stage at rehearsal of an amateur theatrical company, woman director standing addressing seated group of actors.], 1939 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 17 3/8". AA8371 written in blue crayon on verso. Kraft paper cover sheet date stamped NOV 4 1939.
  - 9. [Scene on stage of an amateur theatrical company. Through parted curtains a matron in beret, blouse, and pantaloons reads speech to audience.], 1945 (Box 11, Folder 248)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 22". A9014 written in blue crayon on verso. Kraft paper cover sheet dated in pencil 12-22-45.
  - 10. [Scene on stage at rehearsal of an amateur theatrical company—woman director addressing the actors, all standing.] (Box 11, Folder 249)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 23". A9705 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 11. Does this play have scenery?, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 19 5/8". Caption written in pencil at foot of Kraft paper cover sheet. Date stamped in lower right corner JUN 5 1943. A5605 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 12. "The question is—do we need to fall back on Gilbert & Sullivan or do we want to fall back on Ibsen?", 1944 (Box 11, Folder 250)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 5/8 x 23". Caption and date Nov. 10 - 44 written in pencil at foot of Kraft paper cover sheet. A6925 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 13. But even if we could scare up enough sisters & cousins & aunts, would we be able to scare up enough sailors to go with them?, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 251)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 22". Caption and date Jan 6 '45 written in pencil at foot of Kraft paper cover sheet. A7438 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 14. [Ballet dancer stretches back stage.], 1934 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 12 x 9". In pencil on verso in upper left corner: "Goings-on". AA1571 on 2 written in blue crayon on verso and 3/17/34 written in black crayon.
  - 15. [Scene at rehearsal of amateur theatrical company—woman director below stage addressing actors on stage.], 1938 (Box 11, Folder 252)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 5/8 x 22 5/8". AA8021 written in blue crayon on verso. Stamp on Kraft paper cover: Oct 22 1938.
  - 16. "That's the wrong way to test spark plugs—according to Lieutenant Alice Keogh." (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Pencil, 13 3/4 x 16 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing.
  - 17. "I'll tell you how I buy Defense Bonds. I go without daiquiris!" (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 13 3/4".
  - 18. "Phooey on the little Lapland children!" (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Pencil, 13 3/4 x 16 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. Notation at lower left: "Toy gun in hand."
  - 19. "I don't think I should be required to count the stroke the mosquitoe spoiled, do you?" (Box 11, Folder 253)
    Charcoal on paper, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned.
- Portfolio 6, Series VI
  - 1. "Just think—he's almost old enough to have an Oedipus complex.", 6 (Box 12, Folder 254)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 20 x 15". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above previously erased partially visible caption.
  - 2. "The question is, does this town need planned parenthood?" (Box 12, Folder 255)
    Pencil, 15 x 23 1/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above previously erased partially visible caption. Upper left corner missing.
  - 3. "I only demand two things, Mrs. L'oiselle—excellent material and good lines." (Box 12, Folder 256)
    Pencil, 15 1/8 x 22", unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing with notation—Not Parker—in lower right corner indicating J. R. Parker was not responsible for the caption.
  - 4. Country store. "Mr. Kirby says we don't carry marshmallows—they sell out too fast." (Box 12, Folder 257)
    Pencil, 14 x 23 1/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 5. "I'm trying to use up quite a few things because the moving men are coming tomorrow. " (Box 12, Folder 258)
    Pencil, 15 5/8 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption, and typed on a slip attached to the drawing.
  - 6. "He just doesn't understand conversational French." (Box 12, Folder 259)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 1/8 x 21". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, and cancelled. A5665 written in red crayon on verso.
  - 7. [Two matrons conversing at a dog show—one seated with her feet up, resting on a carrier, the other standing.] (Box 12, Folder 260)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 12 x 22". Portion of lower section of drawing containing the caption cut away. A8511 written in blue crayon on verso and partially cut away.
  - 8. "How gratifying it is that the Archbishop of Canterbury approves of the atomic bomb!" (Box 12, Folder 261)
    Pencil, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption, and typed on a slip attached to the drawing.
  - 9. "Wir wollen keinen Skandal in Edgewood. Das entwertet den Boden.", 1931 (Box 12, Folder 262)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 20". Caption typed on a slip and attached to a strip of brown paper tape covering English caption at foot of drawing. A8416 written in pencil on verso as well as the following: 9/19/31, Miss Helen Hokinson c/o The New Yorker, For Sale $50.00, Insurance $100.00.
  - 10. [At a dog show- a sequence of six panel drawings each of a contestant.] (Box 12, Folder 263)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil; 15 x 20", unsigned. A4068 written in pencil on verso.
  - 11. "You know Dr. Findlay better than I do. Why don't you go in and tell him that his geraniums have a communicable disease." (Box 12, Folder 264)
    Pencil, 14 5/8 x 23 1/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. Accompanied by item 7:126 typed rejection note from James Geraghty.
  - 12. "Tell Mrs. Conklin about the wonderful steaks you had on Okinawa." (Box 12, Folder 265)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 1/2 x 21 3/8". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, with notation—More timely?—in lower right corner. Verso with outline sketch in pencil of two matrons standing conversing with caption written in pencil at foot "Oh, he'll get use to it."
  - 13. "Can't you wait just ten more minutes? You're my foreground." (Box 12, Folder 266)
    Pencil, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing and typed on slip attached to drawing.
  - 14. I don't know the name of the show but I can hum something from it. "I'll never forgive myself for letting Tallulah Bankhead get away!" (Box 12, Folder 267)
    Pencil, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Two captions written in pencil at foot of drawing, the second over a previously erased caption partially visible, and typed on a slip attached to drawing. Notation—another version—in pencil in lower left corner.
  - 15. [Meeting of the ladies club—standing member questions chairman.] (Box 12, Folder 268)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 1/8 x 22 3/4". AC2497 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 16. "I move we all give Mrs. Perry a rising vote of thanks for having made us all want to go right out and start collecting young artists." (Box 12, Folder 269)
    Pencil, 14 x 21 1/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above and over previously erased captions partially visible, and typed on a slip attached to drawing. Notation—(Some Van Goghs & Cezannes by table) This is going on at club now—in pencil in lower right corner.
  - 17. "Turn on your hearing aid, mamma. Mr. Peabody is worth it." (Box 12, Folder 270)
    Pencil, 14 x 23", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing.
  - 18. "Pardon me, would you please put on your hat?" (Box 12, Folder 271)
    Pencil, 15 x 22 1/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing and typed on a slip attached to drawing.
  - 19. [Couple talking to a matron at a social event.] (Box 12, Folder 272)
    Pencil, 15 x 20", rough sketch, unsigned. Several captions written in pencil at foot of drawing and partially erased.
  - 20. "If I subscribe for alternate Wednesdays, I won't get too much Verdi, will I?" (Box 12, Folder 273)
    Pencil, 14 x 23", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 21. "She doesn't know it, but I'm making it formal—gradually." (Box 12, Folder 274)
    Pencil, 15 x 20", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing with notation—2 gardeners—in lower left corner.
  - 22. [Typed note from James Geraghty, art editor of The New Yorker] (Box 10, Folder 172)
    "Dear Miss Hokinson: These ideas were turned down. I would feel badly about it if you didn't have the treasury of undrawn ideas. Geraghty"; initialed JG. 5 x 8". The note was not attached to any particular drawings.
  - 23. "Hurry along with your American bred blood matrons." (Box 12, Folder 275)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 22 3/4", unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. Portion, approximately 9 x 9", cut away from lower right quadrant of drawing.
  - 24. "What is this one supposed to do for me?" (Box 12, Folder 276)
    Pencil, 14 x 23 1/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 26. "Is Josephine H (...) still running?" "Is Judith Anderson still running?" (Box 12, Folder 277)
    Pencil, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Two captions, partially erased, written in pencil at foot of drawing, with notation—Not Parker—in lower right corner. Accompanied by item 6:25, typed rejection note from James Geraghty for sketches 6:26 and 6:27: "Dear Miss Hokinson: These two new ideas were turned down JG."
  - 27. "How do you do. We just wanted to knock on your door & tell you that we love Redding Center." (Box 12, Folder 277)
    Pencil, 14 x 23 1/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over partially erased caption.
  - 28. "you like to buy some luscious tomatoes?" (Box 13, Folder 278)
    Pencil, 15 x 19", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption, partially missing, typed on a slip attached to drawing. Erased caption—written in pencil—partially visible at foot of drawing and partially covered with remains of a typed caption.
  - 29. "Can you hold dinner while Mr. Peabody makes another cocktail? We're all reminiscing about…" (Box 13, Folder 279)
    Pencil, 14 x 23", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing and partially erased.
  - 30. "Why don't you try it on, just for a laugh?" (Box 13, Folder 280)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 23 1/8". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing with notation—Not Parker—in lower right corner.
  - 31. [Matron and spouse at clothing store muffler (scarf) counter.] (Box 10, Folder 173)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 5 1/8 x 7", unsigned. Margins cut away. Drawing relates to #s ll3, 185, 186 in Portfolio #3.
  - 32. [Two sketches of bucking horses—one with a rider.] (Box 13, Folder 281)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 x 22" and 7 3/4 x 10". Most of upper 3/4 of sheet containing horse with rider cut away; the second drawing containing the horse without rider is mounted to the right of the first -drawing. 4871 written in black crayon on verso.
  - 33. "Isn't that a critic from one of the newspapers in front of us?" "Of course not, silly, a critic wouldn't clap." (Box 13, Folder 282)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 x 20". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, and crossed through with notation—fix. A3829 written in pencil on verso.
  - 34. "Oh congratulations, Hilda! There was only a little too much salt in everything tonight!" (Box 4, Folder 52)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 18 1/8", unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption. To the left of drawing is a sketch of Hilda previously erased.
  - 35. "I think she's beginning to look on the bright side of Martha's Vineyard." (Box 13, Folder 283)
    Pencil, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above and over previously erased caption partially visible, and typed on a slip attached to drawing.
  - 36. "But it doesn't say anything to me." "I'm sure my husband would get awfully tired of shepherdesses." (Box 4, Folder 53)
    Pencil, 13 3/4 x 17", rough sketch, unsigned. Two captions written in pencil at foot of drawing over partially visible previously erased caption. Note written in pencil on 3 x 5" slip attached to drawing: "''Are you severe or fluffy?' (Make sure Ross sees they're curtains)."
  - 37. "What is this one supposed to do for me?" (Box 13, Folder 284)
    Pencil, 14 x 20 1/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption partially visible, and typed on a slip attached to drawing.
  - 38. "Would you be able to cope with dotted swiss and ruffles?" (Box 13, Folder 285)
    Pencil, 14 3/8 x 23", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 41. "If I ride up with you to the ninth do you mind if I walk down to the eight?" (Box 13, Folder 286)
    Pencil, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption.
  - 42. "I'm so pleased, my husband is going to put on his dinner jacket for my birthday." (Box 13, Folder 287)
    Pencil, 15 x 21 1/4", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, over previously erased partially visible caption, and typed on a slip attached to drawing. A second caption: "Are you performing any miracles, Mr. Paul?" written in pencil and attached to the drawing.
  - 43. "Of course you understand I don't always have what I bid." (Box 13, Folder 288)
    Pencil, 14 1/2 x 23 1/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption partially visible, and typed on a slip attached to drawing.
  - 44. "Which helps Britain the most, tweeds or whiskey?" (Box 13, Folder 289)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 21 5/8". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased and partially visible captions Notation—This can be changed to dress goods department—written in pencil to the left and above the caption.
  - 45. (with 39 and 40): "Mrs. Harrison Quigley tells me that anyone who cares to see her night-blooming cereus may do so without an appointment." (Box 13, Folder 290)
    Pencil, 15 x 22", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption and above another caption with variant wording- itself over a previously erased caption. Accompanied by captions number 39 & 40: a) typed: "Mrs. Harrison Quigley tells me that anyone who cares to see her night-blooming cereus may do so without an appointment" OR "may do so by appointment"; b) written in pencil: "This is the Dorothy Thompson that we're always getting mixed up with our Dorothy Thompson."; and typed: "This the Dorothy Thompson that we're always getting mixed up with our Dorothy Thompson." 5 x 8"
  - 46. "Let's speak Spanish, so they won't know we're American." (Box 13, Folder 291)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 11". Correction onlay over lower right quadrant of drawing. Caption written in pencil on mat below drawing over previously erased caption with variant wording, and typed on a slip attached to the drawing. See Series VII, drawing 68 for a version intended for a cover.
  - 47. "We aren't going to throw our airplanes until after the Bach, remember?" (Box 13, Folder 292)
    Pencil, 14 3/8 x 23", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing and typed with variant wording on a slip attached to drawing. The slip contains a notation—I'm afraid no other caption matches the action in the drawing—written in pencil below typed caption.
  - 48. "There's only one Bing." (Box 13, Folder 293)
    Pencil, 14 x 22 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased partially visible caption, and typed on a slip attached to drawing. Verso has a light pencil sketch of scene in graveyard.
  - 49. "Herbert, I want to talk with you about these 1927, '28 and '29 Fortune magazines." (Box 13, Folder 294)
    Pencil, 22 x 15", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption, and typed on a slip attached to drawing.
  - 50. "I represent sixteen shareholders who are madder than wet hens!" or…"who are just as mad as we can be." (Box 13, Folder 295)
    Pencil, 14 x 22 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased partially visible caption, with notation—stockholders meeting at left. Typed note: "Dear Miss Hokinson" These two were turned down as I told you yesterday. JG", 5 x 8", attached to drawing.
  - 51. "Clifford, please try not to drop Miss Ogilvie again." (Rehearsing "Ah, Wilderness") (Box 13, Folder 296)
    Pencil, 14 x 23", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, and typed on slip attached to drawing.
  - 52. "And this is the old Roosevelt home." (Box 13, Folder 297)
    Pencil, 15 x 23", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing with notation—White House—at left.
  - 53. "I wanted you to be among the first to sample my own gin and vermouth proportions." (Box 4, Folder 54)
    Pencil, 13 1/2 x 16 7/8", rough sketch, unsigned. Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, and typed on slip attached to drawing.
  - 54. "I want something I won't bulge out of." (Box 13, Folder 298)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 22 1/8". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption. A4026 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 55. "There's a shoe salesman in here who spoils me terribly!" (Box 13, Folder 299)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 22". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption (and above another caption with alternate wording) and typed on a slip attached to the drawing. Pencil-written note also attached: To put on the drawing being held there of two women entering Altman's. "There's a clerk in the shoe/soap/book/greeting card department who spoils me terribly." (I like shoe best).
  - 56. The Turkish Bath (An Intimate Record) (Box 13, Folder 300)
    A sequence of ten panel drawings on three sheets. Black ink and gray wash over pencil, the drawings each approximately 5 x 7" except #10, 5 x 10 3/4", are mounted on sheets 22 x 14 1/8", 22 x 14 1/8", and 17 1/4 x 12 3/4" respectively. Captions written in black ink on overlay sheets to appear at foot of each drawing. Several numbers written on verso.
  - 57. [Two matrons seated in rocking chairs conversing on porch of house at the seashore.], 1936 (Box 13, Folder 301)